[Music]
yeah go for
it hi everyone welcome to the active
inference Institute the textbook reading
group which we hold uh twice every
Thursday and this is the latter group
cohort 8 reading chapter one uh second
week of that and so we're being
introduced to active inference um this
is with chapter one it's uh one of the
shorter chapters of the book of course
it's just opening things up so it
doesn't jump too quickly to say any
complex formalisms or the definition of
expected free energy just yet we're
largely just introduced to sort of uh
the broader Outlook of active inference
is a normative framework for approaching
uh Behavior action inferential
processes uh with a a foundational sort
of neural process Theory and and
functional that is free energy and free
energy minimization so uh quickly we
move to looking at living organisms or
another more uh kind of abstract notion
of that which we now hear all the time
uh for those who work in Ai and Tech uh
agents as a sort of a general notion of
what could be an organism a system of
interest that exhibits Behavior Uh or or
otherwise um agents Tak in sensory
observ ations and elicit actions to
either one realize their desired
outcomes or goals or two to make further
sense of their world by gaining
information this General overview leads
to the development of adaptive behaviors
or strategies agents use for navigating
their environment and this process plays
out in a recursive action perception
cycle where observations inform agents
decision-making regarding the next
action they should take while we may
inure future often view this as a kind
of discrete setting where there are
multiple time steps or Cycles where you
could simulate an agent in reality uh we
tend to view these more as continuous
processes as we're aware that much of
active inference actually derives from
not just the conceptual work and
Mathematics but the direct empirical
work uh friston and others have done
whenever it comes to uh working with
neuroimaging data and dynamic causal
modeling
other forms of looking at continuous
processes over time and linking them
with observed Behavior so these
inference processes or action perception
Cycles can occur at various levels of
complexity and time scales from the
simple and rigid M by moment strategies
of nutrient seeking bacteria to the more
complex and flexible strategies of
humans engaging in planning to realize
their goals in the future potentially
all the way up to Broad cultural and
developmental learning in collectives
societies so um they they give us an
interesting sort of way of viewing
active inference and perhaps why or why
they might justify uh introducing it as
a fully normative framework and so they
frame it as follows uh active inferences
approach is um uh on the side of the
scruffies while scruffies lay emphasis
on the ID pardon me the neats while
scruffies lay emphasis on the
idiosyncrasies and specific ities of
various phenomena of Interest such as
different biological adaptations
neuronal Dynamics or cognitive
mechanisms each deserving separate
bottomup research uh from empirical data
nits aspired to a set of first
principles for explaining and relating
these phenomena in a more top- down
fashion while still engaging an
empirical analysis for validation active
inference also identifies with needs as
it lays a normative framework for
understanding the brain and mind the
biolog and cognitive implications
alongside model design testing for
empirical analysis this is frequently
noticed if anyone uh begins to look at
Journal articles or other Publications
from active inference where sure there
are many times where people are modeling
and remaining within an artificial
environment they may even be intending
to design something that could be used
in the realm of Robotics or uh
artificial intelligence that said there
are many other Behavioral studies done
such as the realm of computational
Psychiatry or classic uh uh lab studies
with with Myer rodents where there is
indeed forms of model fitting and
revision of the model based upon the
actual empirical data that is collected
shouldn't leave out also other
continuous State space and hybrid State
space um examples including studying
things like is secades and um
neuroimaging data fluctuation and
electrography and so on and we do have a
question so yeah John go for
it uh yeah this confused me every time I
read it why why is it called a normative
framework it seems to associate
normative framework with first
principles I've never heard an
association like that before I hoping
someone could
clarify that's interesting yeah is that
we could open up to discussion if anyone
has any thought on that um otherwise I
can go for it
yeah is this a we could think of it as
sort of an expression of natural law
just a this is a physical Dynamic
principle yeah go for so um I mean as
far as normative in the sense of
establishing a norm my take there on on
this specific point is that this is in
fact providing like a an attempt at a
holistic framework where there are a
variety of Concepts that are introduced
not necessarily uh introduced aresh as
active inference draws from a variety of
disciplines um but nonetheless it it
does attempt to build up something like
potentially totalizing picture of how we
could View Behavior Uh
inference uh and anything from
biological to other physical uh and
psychological phenomena so in that sense
it is drawing from first principles
because it needs to establish certain
principles of how to achieve that
framework and maintain it and like on
which it the framework relies and then
normative I I I see those as rather part
partial um so so that's been my take on
it so if I switched normative for
holistic I couldn't go too far wrong do
you think I mean I would say so yeah
just curious though because this might
be helpful for others too um I mean what
what is your because I'm looking at a
quick definition of normative just to
kind of lay some some connection here
that that we can all work with
establishing relating to or deriving
from a standard or Norm especially
Behavior so we do have like kind of an
establishment of like this is how this
is our Norm that we have for viewing
behavior um holistic sure sure that that
could work as well
yeah yeah this is a really interesting
question and I'm sure unless there's
some British connotation or something
peculiar
which is I think a great starting point
for discussion but it's not a
declarative you know so it's it's it's
all just language samples but it's like
what is normative about how things
actually are I mean are things not as
they normally are according to like
Central limit theorem in the limit of
large
classical things are described by Norms
especially if we're not going to be
interpolating
um secondary functions like reward
functions that has been applied even in
the social like social scripts and
expectations theory of mind and that's
not even necessarily ACM that's just
like expectations and norms and
firstness and inertia and there just has
to be an overwhelming element of
things identifiable things being
identifiably as they are
so that's and then there's a sort of
interpretation of like modeling practice
normativity like you ought to consider
multi-agent systems or but those might
have those don't necessarily have
axiomatic there might be very good
epistemic hygiene or modeling strategies
or machine learning or interpretability
or anything like or
performance um or model efficacy or
something but I but it's a little
different than and also what first Prin
principles
are
Stephen yeah I think uh Andrew did a
good job of
uh probing what the issue is there are
definitions of what normally
normalizing is as a scaling but
also uh what
you're referring to is the mindset first
principles the normative first
principles are you know energy
entropy uh principles and
that's what uh the way it's used here I
think it's a it's a fun another
principle yeah yeah know that's really
well said Stephen it's uh because it's
yeah and what Daniel pointed to
referring to social scripts and things
like that I mean it the word normative
not that I'm necessarily an momology but
I mean it's been used in a variety of
contexts and I personally have like this
sort of General social sciences
background before I I kind of took a
turn into kind of the harder Sciences as
well as data and empirical data um but
uh so so normative has also been used in
many contexts to refer as something that
is culturally normative meaning it's
it's almost as if you're saying oh
doesn't really rely upon anything other
than the fact that we do it and
influence one another such that it's a
social phenomena of you know that that
that is normative in our society but
perhaps not in other societies versus
what I view active inference which is
saying you know I mean I don't want to
open things up and make it too abstract
but it's kind of like it's as if freston
friston at all here are saying that
where kind of putting up this normative
framework perhaps you choose perhaps you
know perhaps it's a choice that you
decide to kind of borrow into this
framework at least I mean in our context
obviously you know this is not a very
authoritarian authoritative uh command
rather it's just in the same way we
spoke at the beginning of the session
just prior that this can be a kind of
toolkit uh for people you know it's your
choice ultimately if you decide to agree
with the entirety of the framework and
i' honestly advise that you not do that
if you've only read the first few pages
of chapter one you should spend more
time with it as you should with anything
before fully buying into it but um I
think it provides a pretty strong
argument personally um you could maybe
guess that given I'm here but um yeah so
so there's a lot of nuance to to the
word normative but I I think this is in
some ways it's like an offering of a
full framework that's been worked on for
at least a couple of decades now and
arguably longer if we kind of Trace
the lineage there um and uh yeah it's a
rather holistic
view reading that question um that
I uh I'll put in the chat this was just
as as usual the notes are scattered so
again it's just a starting point but
here's another
interesting uh view was
[Music]
um the term normative this could have
been in alism or something the term
normative means there is some evaluative
standard against which behavior can be
scored active inference is normative in
the sense that perception and action are
scored by free energy a quantity we will
unpack through this in the next chapters
actually maybe that's just from the
book or a
footnote but that's just one way of them
even saying it so it again it's like you
can always just say okay does it really
matter even what we think about this one
English word doesn't it matter more what
it's actually going to be not just um um
zooming in only on one adjective just
because we wouldn't have written it that
way in our
view but giving norms and measurement
giving a measure
theory of information spaces which is
more like the basing
mechanics
view there's a gauge and a norm and and
measurements that that get
but if we're not if we're not clear if
we're talking
about inculturation normativity or
mathematical gauge and like sheath then
I mean then it's just too broad to be
useful it's just not
a yeah I just didn't know what was
intended by that word because I've never
seen that word in context like that
before sure sure yeah I it's it's it's
been used in philosophy as well at
certain points to distinguish like oh
this is a a normative framework in the
sense of it it is making claims about
something that you necessarily have to
agree with in order to actually get
something out of or to like properly
utilize the framework um it's not used
in that way 100% of the time though um
so actually a lot of the ambiguity
around the word normative here yeah just
uh it's quite broad could uh could go
many ways but I I hope yeah so anyway I
hope that the perhaps the word holistic
is a a fair enough interpretation of the
word um it I think it adds to it if it
doesn't Encompass everything it probably
doesn't Encompass everything so
um does anyone else have any any
thoughts or questions or anything they'd
like to throw out there
[Music]
okay
um so in reference to some of what we
discussed as well at the very beginning
of the session so this chapter of course
remains rather brief relative to others
and uh as we're just being introduced
and so of course in a nice fashion
they're nice enough to uh give us the
outline of the book so the book is
separated into two parts the first half
focuses on Theory which I know many will
be quite interested in as opposed to the
second half uh this first half acts as a
broad primer which covers active
inference as a normative framework with
its distinct Concepts and theories the
second half will cover practice by
describing examples of core active
inference models with their components
and examples of applications as well as
information needed for Designing novel
models and uh what they also don't
mention involves a model analysis and
potential fitting and other perspectives
we can take on the modeling process
itself so we're provided a conceptual
road map for coming to an understanding
of active active inference in the first
half of this book which could be
followed along a low road starting from
basis theorem or a high road starting
from what is known as the free free
energy principle so the the low road
especially it supplies the mechanics of
active inference in its relation to the
basian brain hypothesis whereby
inference is seen to work by way of
basis theorem so we have uh in basis
theorem we have prior information about
hidden States we have a likelihood
distribution describing how they relate
to
observations and then we have new
observations themselves as evidence
which can be brought together
to all compute posterior beliefs about
in States then on the other hand with
chapter three we'll get into the free
energy principle necessity for agents to
minimize this quantity as a proxy or
upper bound on surprisal in order to
survive and adapt to their environment
whereby the tractable proxy allows for V
variational inference and can certainly
relate to many Notions of things like
metabolism uh you know saving of
resources
expenditure um actually being able to
accomplish physiologically neurobiologic
neurobiologically or otherwise different
kinds of inference processes that
otherwise may not work or be very very
strenuous to an organism to to
accomplish if they they could actually
run it in full uh as if they could
activate every neuron in their brain
simultaneously and then finally
eventually we we'll get to chapter four
uh which gets us back on the low roads
Foundation and bases theorem so there
will be a bit of a cross back to return
to that previous material we're
introduced to two template models used
in active inference especially uh the
these two exemplars the first being a
PDP in discrete time scenarios and we'll
also look at continuous time scenarios
where we instead rely a bit more on on
on different differential equations or
tailor series approximation in chapter 5
uh that's kind of the meat of active
inference as far as sort of making these
connections to neurobiological processes
goes we'll look a lot at uh variational
message passing and uh their
relationship to cortical circuitry and
the sort of passing of
information as well as uh being able to
see how some of the concepts will be
introduced to along the way such as
ideas of precision um and other model
components relate to neurobiology in the
form of synaptic gain uh
neurotransmitters and so on so um from
there the chapter starts to wrap up and
we see that U active inferences approach
to various Concepts and con mechanisms
such as perception which is changing
one's mind and action is changing the
world learning is similar to perception
but operating at a slower time scale
with longer term impact on the inference
process so we have a separation
separation between inference and
learning in this framework then planning
is a means of selecting a actions in
sequences to realize future goals if I
want some uh food I'm going to have to
take several steps to get there thus
devising my own policy which can then be
compared to other policies um and then
we also can break that up those policies
and the way I select them in terms of
exploration and exploitation um do I
want to try a new restaurant do I want
to try something different along the way
do I want to stop and look online at uh
local restaurants before even getting
straight to the goal of actually like
attaining nourishment uh so so it's it's
it's worthwhile to consider like in an
everyday sense given the sort of holism
of this framework you know how can we
relate it to everyday things I've just
seen that as being useful for as a is a
sort of learning horis uh for people who
still who are still new to thinking in
these these kinds of ways and um so on
so let's see I think it's worthwhile to
given the amount of time we have left
it's worthwhile to just kind of open it
up from there uh if anyone had any
particular questions they want to pursue
further they have a certain section in
the in the textbook that particularly
piqu their
interest um we can always go to the
questions for the chapter that have been
asked historically Beyond this group so
anyone feel free to recommend
anything so the way this works is you
try to update your beliefs first and if
that's not good enough then can you act
to change the
world not
necessarily um so but that is a good
question uh because it's really
important to clarify those two things so
an active inference it's as if at any
given moment someone could be doing both
of these things
simultaneously um that is uh I I could
be seeing something and then I associate
that with a hidden State set of hidden
States or otherwise to to finding the
beliefs uh that I have about you know
what what goes beyond what I'm seeing
like what something means and then
simultaneously I can act right so if I'm
sitting here I'm thirsty and then I look
over and I see that my water bottle is
there and I have a belief that you know
I had put water in it and that it is
available to me all the way down to this
highly granular level that likely
involves a lot of inferential processes
that I am not at all explicitly thinking
about because it's such this is such
habitual behavior for me so I don't have
to put that much effort in but if I
actually thread it out word it in this
way that there's a kind of perceptual in
inference process going on and
simultaneously I want water so I'm like
kind of driven towards something so I
also take this water bottle to be a kind
of affordance to me that I can then you
know proceed to act and I can pick it up
um and I could go straight for the drink
or I could actually look inside of it
first to get more information about if
it even has water in water in it or not
prior to Jumping straight to the kind of
pragmatic value of consuming the
beverage um so so yeah if if that makes
sense it's like these things can play
out simultaneously and presumably they
are all of the time so uh my body has a
variety of circuitry within it where
inferential processes can potentially be
taking place or you know you could view
the mind as is doing that many ways
through different cortical layers um
passing messages between them inferring
different things and uh so on so did
that give any clearer picture I'll add
one thing that was very interesting
Andrew is uh the the physics like basy
and mechanics is in terms of uh
simultaneous unfolding flow Dynamics
kind of like a heat bath situation with
unfolding flows that might be sampled
from whereas especially if you're going
to be writing an implementation that
runs on a single core
CPU there will be some
sequential logic or program
flow so there's actually a lot of
degrees of freedom in between the
analytical representations which are
basically unopinionated on what order
you do what actual
implementations and so there's like this
like UDA Loop or the test operate test
exit
all these different ways of thinking
about well does this happen first or
when does this belief updating
happen it is certainly not specified
like that in the general part of the
theory because it's to be specified in
the specific parts of the
theory I think it's probably also
important to remember there are
hierarchical orders of
organization you know from
the on the physical level
and subatomic
Atomic up through on the biological
scale
Cellular Systems organism these
different levels of organization have
their own characteristic
Dynamics and so if you're speaking with
the language of the organismal level say
the mind
level
of having preconceptions with constant
updating based
on activity sensory and motor
activity that's a different hierarchical
level than say on
the uh thermodynamic chemical level
where you might want to model it
differently implementation might be
slightly different but here's the here's
here's what I I'm really interested Ed
in the difference between the normative
principle or the holistic
framework versus the
implementation uh whether it's modeling
like you're saying Daniel on a single
core system or uh just algorithmically
like how to set up the implementation of
what we're considering to be a a general
holistic uh just natural law principle
of how things work
and and to that end if I can Circle back
to the
definitional clarifications we were
trying to get at in the
beginning uh Andrew how do you go
through the meta metacognitively
metacognitive uh process of like uh
doing online translations of these words
like the action and the
inference uh when you're applying it in
a specific
uh case or
application yeah to to be clear do you
mean to say in the in the sense of like
if I were actually going to sit down and
engage in some kind of cognitive
modeling or do you mean like just the
literal translation a moment ago of me
describing picking up a a glass of of
water yeah e either one would work just
either one yeah cool uh no that
uh and that and I'll also say that the
two would kind of borrow from one
another um so maybe I can since it is a
personal question uh which I appreciate
maybe I will just I'll just go for it
um let's see so what really helped me
personally when engaging in like
actually attempting to model something
which so for anyone who is interested in
modeling to the degree of they want to
program themselves
um a lot of active inference modeling uh
there are growing numbers of resources
and tools for accomplishing that I kind
of starts with friston's work in the mat
lab language and and building his own um
SPM uh package for that and U I'll I'll
I'll skip ahead a little bit and say
that um to actually start developing
something where you can simulate an
organism or agent within its environment
like actually kind of coding that up uh
as a simulation then watching it play
out and watching these kind of like
algorithmic steps that play out I think
it's highly informative like in that
kind of intuitive sense of like and also
active inference would say this as well
right we're not just passive observers
we actively engage with the world
including to seek information so all I
mean to say with that is by actually
sitting down to do the cognitive
modeling that actually filled in a lot
of gaps for me not to say that someone
who doesn't program could never
understand active inference certainly
not the case uh we've had so many people
who don't know how to code and yet they
have very kind of Rich backgrounds uh in
in philosophy and psychology and so on
right now I'm working on a project with
um some folks at The Institute where one
of them is a clinical therapist and so
I'm kind of playing the role of the the
computational psychiatrist where we're
devising a model together
which relies upon active inference
foundational uh kind of first principles
perspective on how to do this and then
the clinical therapist has reported uh
information from from Anonymous uh well
they know them but redacted from the
final study uh participants they engaged
with who all of whom had uh were
diagnosed at one point with
PTSD so whenever I sit down to think
about how to model that and of course
this is very sensitive subject matter so
I don't really take it lightly to just
sit down and think oh yeah I can just
make a person who exhibits all the
characteristics of PTSD and then one
sitting let alone like you know I would
want to fit that model to real world
phenomena for example
obviously um so all that
said um I guess with perception and
action you know like I said earlier it
tends to play out in a continuous
setting in reality but if we're going to
set up kind of a sequential like step by
step like following the classic roles of
like developing models that are not too
complex while still being uh uh accurate
like a kind of einsteinian you know
simple as possible but no simpler sort
of approach then then it becomes useful
to especially in the case of modeling a
person who might have kind of these
discret beliefs with their own relative
strengths um I would view it as you know
this is this is a discret per time step
multiple time steps per trial of the
simulation um you know I view it as like
there's an action perception Loop so
first and it could have your starting
point it doesn't matter right it's like
presumably this Loop is infinitely
recurring so to speak until it can't
anymore because something happened with
your biology to where you don't exist
anymore you lost the part that's doing
the inference or otherwise um but it
would begin with something in an
algorithmic fashion as something like an
agent engages with their Environ in the
sense of they sense something from the
uh from the environment so they take in
an observation as it were they they
could see it it could be Inception and
they they feel it or even notice a
signal coming from within uh
exteroceptive sensation would be that
the seeing it you know the the more
typical way of viewing it is like oh we
have five senses and one of them is
touch and one of them is taste and so on
that that would be more exteroceptive
we'd also have proprioceptive in the
sense of you know physical movement
which uh uh you know as far as we
understand the brain I mean it that has
its own distinct set of Dynamics so on
um in any case you you take in some kind
of um observation and then from there
you update your beliefs right it's as if
your mind is processing that information
you know we can imagine it very much in
a real- time setting and so it's there
that these inference processes play out
what does that water bottle that I saw
mean right and then
uh and then from there I can decide what
to do about that fact or it doesn't have
to be about that fact it might just be
that I saw it but but nonetheless what
am I what am I going to do right now I
could choose to do nothing I continue
sitting here right it a null action is
still an action as it were we're always
doing something um and then the cycle
just kind of well final important part
that that I'm no longer responsible for
once I ch an action you know I do that
action and then that reciprocally
impacts the environment around me so if
I just sit here uh you know you all will
see me sitting here and uh and and
there's not much going on I could jump
up and dance around for no reason and
upset all of my neighbors in my
apartment complex I suppose that's
another thing I could do which would
then I would would elicit probably an
observation to me of someone knocking on
my door telling me to keep it down or
maybe they're more polite than that but
anyway but you can see the point right
it's like it's you're able to once you
kind of get the the notion of the action
perception Loop down and get a a fair
intuitive intuitive enough grasp of the
concepts you can kind of start to become
much more granular with it view it as a
series of processes and then whenever
you want to model something then it
suddenly like that can give you that
kind of grasp of like oh this is how I
would model like this is how I would
drill down into trying to understand
these kinds of behaviors that I want to
see such as me looking at PTSD and
getting a verbal description from uh you
know a uh a qualitative study uh
participant who has PTSD describing how
their day tends to go or how do they
react in particular circumstances you
know with PTSD it's like people get um
triggered um and so and I I actually
have it myself so there's a there's a
personal interest there uh for me and so
um to to actually be able to look at the
behavior and then consider like what is
happening there what what what is
distinct about that and then if we start
to view model parameters actually as you
know these kind of things a generative
model that we have that allows us to
navigate the world around us and engage
in different things then suddenly those
parameter values become incredibly
important because if they become too
misaligned suddenly I start engaging in
different kinds of suboptimal behavior
or someone else would right
so um they you the idea of M repeatedly
making the same mistake over and over
despite getting evidence showing you
that you should not be doing something
or you should should be doing something
right it's in that case that it's kind
of like we can start to view a model is
something that is kind of just you know
engaging in a certain behavior and it's
actually the parameter values and the
construction of the model that that kind
of determin it's its sort of Fitness or
optimality for the task at hand you know
so you can imagine know someone who who
who has ADHD and might have some kind of
difficulty with with concentrating and
and emotional regulation and so whenever
they try to engage in Social settings
they might struggle with engaging in the
conversation in the fashion that uh they
would actually like to like there's
there's a difference between what we
think and what we do right um so so it
might be that due to particular
characteristics of their neurobi
neurobiology synaptic transmission and
so on uh it might be kind of preventing
them or kind of skewing them towards
certain kinds of Behavior Uh both
internally and externally that that
don't actually meet meet the
situation uh it's around here that I
think anyone who's interested in things
like actually something very a very
different example which is machine
learning would suddenly like you know
their ears would perk up because they'd
be thinking about how this is a model
that is making poor predictions and so
it's act behaving in a very suboptimal
way relative to the sort of purpose or
or or intent of the model if we could
use the word intent there because I've
been talking about humans so much um so
very long explanation but I I hope I
hope that was useful and and maybe
interesting to at least some of you um
and it has been fun talking in these
kinds of ways with with people who are
you know with the clinical therapist I
you know who I'm doing the research
pract like the research group um with so
yeah hey Andrew yes um in this chapter
you also mentioned it and they don't say
much about
learning um that's something I'm I am
very interested in I actually I came to
active inference from this paper of
laa de
Pao about um active inference I think
it's called active inference goes goes
to school about large language
models uh in
education um so I'm like very interested
in um the notion of learning in in
active
inference
um because it's seems to me that it's
like very fundamental aspect of living
organisms so maybe you can say a little
bit about that or and also I don't know
if uh if it's something that goes more
into detail in the next chapters and I
would like to a little bit about
learning yeah yeah definitely no
absolutely and yeah I think I think part
of why they don't go too far into
learning is in part uh and I I'll focus
more on actually directly answering your
question but I think they maybe don't
they Dodge going too quickly into it in
chapter one just because we're already
being presented with at face value like
this is a normative framework and
they're you know it's going to take time
to get up to there and then furthermore
I think by explaining inference itself
as its own process it it it it's a good
introduction prior to getting into
learning which is where instead of like
with inference we we update our beliefs
to get these in a basian framework these
posterior beliefs it's like your prior
beliefs of what you you thought before
versus you know some kind of Engagement
with the world through perception or
action then you end up with what you
think after but we can view learning as
a very similar process perhaps it
happens at a slower time scale um you in
most modeling it it very much is you
know you could almost think of it as the
difference between short long-term
memory if we put them in caricature a
little bit just for the sake of example
um but um so so learning would be like
that it will first of all the the
textbook most certainly will get much
more into learning um I think there's a
significant amount of it in the second
half of the book um because it because
of the kind of distinctness of it when
ever engaging in actually building
models and S simulating them with
programming or otherwise however it will
get into it much earlier on uh as well
so so rest assured it'll it'll come up
soon enough um
yeah and and this is also a rather
interesting looking paper I came across
this at one point because I've also do
some work with llms and I'll briefly
mention that we've actually had talks
previously with with Ben White as well
as AAL who I think just did one a few
days ago um okay Axel constant we know
Andy Clark yeah anyway sorry and I think
also La was in the yeah did had had one
time with
Laura um there's also this common double
usage of terms from um learning
attention memory and like are they being
applied to the person and like the real
question of human learning in a bigger
form or in it's sort of narrower just
like parameter updating belief updating
but that's not necessarily like the
experiential qualia
belief um yeah this was this was yeah a
great um paper and it's a good direction
to keep
exploring yeah yeah that's um and also
the question you you put in the in the
chat it's it's like a very core question
of to think about how
this uh framework can INF form certain
practices uh in the case of education
but there might be
another
um
practical um cases where this framework
might inform how to use certain
Technologies in this case AI systems but
so very I'm going to watch that for
sure yeah most definitely I mean it's
active inference is only more ever
increasingly more broadly being applied
to phenomena that when I first came to
it personally I was not necessarily
interested in myself I mean I whenever I
first started I was quite new to
computer programming to machine learning
or anything along those I keep bringing
that up because active inference it has
heavy overlap with with reinforcement
learning um but also yeah just just
Behavioral
aspects of engaging with different
things right now I'm uh I've been giving
feedback to someone who's writing a
draft on applying this L quite directly
to the idea of like human uh
technological kind of intera interaction
we're looking at socio Technical Systems
looking at technology is a sort of
potential mediator of our interactions
with one another and um it's it's really
fascinating and it's it's just the the
kind of Concepts that come in the first
part or first half of this book
um you know with with spending a little
bit of time with them they start to
provide just sort of a lot of fodder or
or or at least at least initial
inspirational material for thinking
about these things in this way um you
know when you and of course in
philosophy there are a lot of theories
of things like this like extended
cognition uh you know the idea that is
is the fact that an imense amount of
information on the internet that can
then be you know transmitted and
received by your phone and then phone
being in your pocket therefore you have
this wealth of knowledge in your pocket
at any given moment like uh what does
that say about us if we do agree with
this idea that we we infer and learn and
at some point we end and and something
else begins like an agent in their
environment you'll see a concept later
that becomes really important in active
inference there have been various
discussions and even debates about it so
it's worth being aware of that um what
it is called a marov blanket so
um I personally don't get
to heavy emphasis upon the word
personally um I don't get too caught up
in the heavy specifics of it there are
many heavy like very precise specifics
about it it relates partially to Judea
pearls theory of the marov blanket but
but it's used a bit differently here in
active inference uh but one way of
viewing it is simply that it's it's a
way of kind of separating an agent or
organism or whatever your system of
interest is from what it is not um
because those who are familiar with any
kind of modeling are surely aware and I
was too because I did my own forms of
economic modeling and kind of social
science oriented modeling before I I
came to active inference it's like yeah
like I'm looking at data and information
and it gets processed in different ways
and I have to decide what something
isn't in order to study it and it seems
like such a simple thing and then of
course like for a modeler it's like you
know you you still have to make certain
kinds of definitive statements over what
your system is versus what is the not
system as I've heard uh some researchers
say like you have a system and a not
system you have an agent you have an
environment you have uh a generative
model then you have the generative
process in which that generative model
kind of interacts so
um yeah and so with socio Technical
Systems and interaction between a human
and an
llm so you know it's kind of like the
the hum oh yeah go ahead sorry I was
gonna say that that's fascinating
um uh maybe I will ask you for some
references uh regarding that because
um yeah as I as I said in the intro it's
like
I I use these kind of
Frameworks as a lens to understand
certain things especially regarding
technology so that's why I like the this
paper and
also uh work by Ben White in
poito um because it's like a way of
understanding how
we uh embodied beings kind of in
interact with Technologies and how we're
affected by it but also how we shape
them and I think that's but also comes
this point you're you're you're
mentioning like where does the techn
technological environment ends and we
start uh and that's a good question if
you are trying to think
about uh even different questions on
ethics and regulations right how where
do you put that line and so yeah maybe I
will send you an email for some
references because I think this is um
very uh close to my work very very
interesting cool yeah no looking forward
to it it's it's been a lot of fun
getting more involved with the The
Institute and I I notice uh folks have
been asking me many questions but I I
welcome them so please go for it I
already here and we we're about to have
to wrap up here unfortunately but I look
forward to next week but I just noticed
here llms could be powerful educative
tools in the hands of teachers
augmenting the growing skilled
capabilities of children here's an
example of how this might look like uh
as a child is engaged in a writing task
rather than making auto corrections the
system could highlight mistakes draw the
child's attention and suggest helpful
resources for self-correct
so this is me not having read the paper
though I believe I've skimmed it at one
point um here's an example a child is
engaged in writing task there's a task
there's a goal here we have the the
makings of a behavioral task or
experiment uh right before us rather
than making autoc Corrections which
would be where the llm does something
that the child otherwise would do the
system could highlight mistakes drawing
the child's attention attention is
highly implicated in active inference I
think many people who do anything
related to to Neuroscience you know get
interested in attention at some point or
another as do those who work on modeling
in fact people who who build llms are
concerned with things like an attention
mechanism that the llm either has within
it or is you know kind of has is
equipped with um so so so this is
proposing at face value at least but I I
I feel like it's rather accurate
uh is something like uh Le trying to
devise a way of integrating Ln such that
they augment the child's ability to
actually actively learn it helps to
point out where the mistake is so they
can you know over time learn how to
identify the mistakes themselves and
then also they have to do the work to
correct it themselves as well which I
think so the notion is this is providing
more fulfilling you know uh learning
experience but then also they're they're
really paying attention to the sort of
terminology you know there is a task at
hand there is something that needs to be
corrected there are attentional
mechanisms in place so and then suggest
helpful resources like this is providing
them with what we might call epistemic
value or Information Gain or just simply
this is helping them to also learn
additional information in addition to
just uh correcting mistake it's like oh
here's more info that can help me going
forward and they then they themselves
have to actually click on the link or
whatever happens you know it's just
making the suggestion so this this
prevents the LM for from becoming an
additional organ on the child that they
now have to always rely upon right if
you want to view it in that kind of
human techn technology interaction it's
like instead of making this a necessary
organ that you're always going to need
it in order to write anything because
now you're highly dependent upon
autocorrect instead it's helping to
augment your education ability to write
by simply giving you some starting steps
on getting uh used to identifying
mistakes and then seeking out further
resources whenever you're not sure what
to do that was my little four minute of
a a summary of a paper I still need to
read myself but it looks really
interesting so so thanks for sharing
this and yeah feel free to reach out and
then we also The Institute has a Discord
uh and so you're you're welcome to reach
me there uh it's well and then I will
also ideally be around uh for next
week's
textbook group as well so sounds good
one week today yeah thank you
Andrew thank you everyone so yeah this
time slot next time will
be
um chapter
7 discreet time which again interleaving
them is totally good and and
useful but if you want to continue with
chat with the early part of the book
then it's going to be earlier next week
so and vice vers so thank you though see
you all later